Guide to the Southern Cone Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Southern Cone collection
1779-1995
1779-1941
MS 1778
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.25
(10 boxes)
A collection of correspondence; government documents; published illustrated materials; and writings from the Southern Cone region of Latin America (Argentina, Paraguay, Uruguay) on civil, military, economic and social topics.
Existence and Location of Copies
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2013-M-023, is available on microfilm and may be purchased from Gale Group, Farmington Hills, Michigan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials have been assembled from various collections and acquired from several individuals. They include materials transferred from the Latin American Collection Curator, Yale University Library, 2012-2015.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 2013-M-023, is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 251 instead of the originals.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by country, and by date within country.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence; government documents; published illustrated materials; and writings from the Southern Cone region of Latin America (Argentina, Paraguay, Uruguay). The collection is arranged by country, and by date within country. The description of each item includes, when possible, its author, title, place of origin, and a summary of its contents. When an item is a copy of an original, it is arranged by the date of the original. The date field, however, contains the date of the copy itself, not the original. The date of the original is included in the summary description of the item.
Argentina -- Civilization -- Italian influences; Argentina -- History -- 1776-1810; Argentina -- History -- 1817-1860; Argentina -- History -- 1860-1910; Argentina -- History -- War of Independence, 1810-1817; Paraguay -- History -- 1811-1870; Paraguay -- History -- To 1811; Paraguay -- History -- War of Independence, 1810-1811; Uruguay -- History -- To 1810; San Martín, José de, 1778-1850
- Inventory, 1779-1988
  Scope and Contents
  The collection is comprised of originals and copies of materials from Argentina, Paraguay and Uruguay. The majority pertain to Argentinian history from the late eighteenth century to the middle of the present century. Of particular significance is a nineteenth century bound volume bearing the imprint "De Don Jose San Martin." It contains numerous handwritten passages drawn from philosophical texts, religious and political treatises, as well as literary works, which reflect the education and thinking of this leader of South American independence. A summary of documents dealing with the abortive Alzaga rebellion, written by the acting Viceroy, discusses the political situation in Argentina just prior to independence. Materials about Buenos Aires's La Boca neighborhood are useful for the study of Italian immigration to Argentina, and the history of the Argentine-Italian community. Of note regarding Paraguay are handwritten copies of several little-known texts that deal with the country's history in the early nineteenth century.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Patrons must use microfilm on FILM HM 251 instead of the originals.
  - Argentina
    - Title: Novedades de Buenos Aires. Place: Buenos Aires. Description: Notice of the arrival of a ship, believed to have been lost on an expedition along the Patagonian coast, bringing news of further discoveries and of a potential English presence in the region., 1779 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - Author: Linier, Santiago de. Title: Summary by the viceroy of the Rio de la Plata. Place: Buenos Aires. Description: Summary of the contents of documents sent to the Spanish Crown which deal with the abortive rebellion led by Martin de Alzaga and prior events in Buenos Aires. Also discussed is the situation in Montevideo involving Francisco Elio, British and Portuguese involvement in the area, and events in Spain., 1809 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Testimonio del expediente obrado sobre el apresamiento de la fragata Triton y su cargamento, correspondiente a Real Compania de Filipinas...." Place: Buenos Aires. Description: Documents dealing with the seizure of the Triton by the navy of the United Provinces of La Plata. The ship belonged to the Royal Spanish Company of the Philippines and was sailing from Calcutta to Cadiz. Included are a cargo manifest, testimonies by sailors and translations of papers in English taken from the Triton., 1817 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Congreso de las Provincias Unidas del Rio de la Plata" Place: Buenos Aires? Description: Speech calling for an end to civil wars and for the people to accept the new constitution. The discourse condemns Simon Bolivar for creating a despotic state in Bolivia and his occupation of the province of Tarija., 1826 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by Juan Manuel de Rosas to Manuel Jose Garcia. Place: Rio Colorado. Description: Rosas acknowledges receipt of Garcia's letter of November 7 and states that he will shortly answer the letters of Mr. Guido. Includes typescript transcription and English translation., 1833 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Letter by Jose Justo de Urquiza to Marcelo Cerrutti. Place: San Jose. Description: Letter by Jose Justo de Urquiza to the "Encargado de Negocios" of the king of Sardinia thanking him for his offer of assistance with European correspondence. A newspaper clipping about Urquiza is attached to the letter., 1857 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - Author: Sarmiento, Domingo Faustino Title: Tumba de Piñero. Place: Buenos Aires? Description: Handwritten copy or draft of a speech delivered by Domingo Faustino Sarmiento in honor of Senator Martin Piñero. Written on the official stationery of the Argentinian president., Circa 1870s-1880s (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - Author: Pelliza, Mariano A. Title: The War for Argentine Independence. Place: Buenos Aires? Description: Published broadside concerning attempts by Argentinian armies to liberate northwestern Argentina and Bolivia from Spanish rule between 1809 and 1813., 1879 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - Title: Compiled writings. Place: Buenos Aires? Description: A bound handwritten volume containing transcribed passages from philosophical texts, religious and political treatises, as well as prose passages and poetry. Texts are in Spanish, English and French. All transcriptions appear to be written in the same hand. A bookplate on the inside cover bears the imprint "De Don Jose San Martin.", [18--?] (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Author: Moneta, Jose Manuel. Place: Buenos Aires. Title: "La Argentina fué el primer país que estableció el correo Antártico." Description: Newspaper article from La Prensawhich asserts Argentine sovereignty in Antarctica. It details the establishment of mail services in the Antarctic regions in 1904., 1941 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Los Cuentos de la Boca." Description: A collection of materials related to a documentary about the history of La Boca, an old Italian neighborhood in Buenos Aires. Included is a copy of the documentary; background information about the film; a brief history of La Boca; copies of photographs used in the film; photographs of the filming of the production; and copies of clippings from Italian newspapers about the film.
      - Background materials, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
      - Original, 1 (Box 1)
      - Duplicating master (Box 1D)
      - Use copy, 1 (Box 1U)
  - Paraguay
    - Author: Da Costa, Pacidonio, et. al. Title: "Primer ensayo sobre la historia del Paraguay por..." Description: Handwritten copy of several different texts which detail Paraguayan history from colonization to 1824; Paraguay's political situation in 1811-1812; and the re-establishment, reform and natural order of the "Jesuitic System" in Paraguay through 1823. Also included are an exchange of diplomatic correspondence between Brazil and Paraguay; part of the political catechism for Paraguayan youth; and correspondence between Jose Artigas, leader of Uruguay, and Juan Martin Pueyrredon, the leader of Argentina. (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Uruguay
    - Title: Documents concerning shipping. Description: Two sets of documents dealing with shipping and naval affairs between Spain and Montevideo. The ships Anunciación and Los Dos Hermanos de Montevideo Victorio y Francisco are prominently discussed., 1785-1805 (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - Title: "Cartas dedicadas a el recto honorable Lord N ? sobre las ultimas expediciones a la costa española....," Place: London? Description: Handwritten Spanish language copy, made by a Latin American resident of Britain, of five letters addressed to an unidentified English lord. These letters, by an unidentified author, discuss the characteristics of the area's people; the threats posed by Napoleon Bonaparte; and United States involvement in the region and why it was in Britain's interest to get involved in the emancipation of the Americas. The writer proposes a plan for England to seek an independent Mexico., 1807 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 14, Reel 1U)
- Additional material, Circa 1860-1890; Accession 2013-M-023
  This accession consiststs of published illustrated scenes of Buenos Aires, Argentina.
  - Description: Two illustrations depicting Argentinian soldiers; one illustration depicting two women and a man wearing traditional Paraguayan dress; and one illustration of the Buenos Aires harbor and cityscape. Illustrators: P. Blanchau, James Langer, unknown. Publication: L'Illustration, Journal Universel, pages 296-297., Circa 1860-1880 (Box 1)
  - Description: One illustration depicting the Rio Della Plata, and one illustration depicting the Piazza Della Victoria in Buenos Aires. Illustrators: unknown. Publication: L'Illustrazione Italiana, page 77., Circa 1860-1880 (Box 1)
  - Title: "View of the City of Buenos Ayres, Argentine Republic." Illustrator: A.C.S. Publication: unknown., Circa 1860-1880 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Plaza Del Mercato A Buenos Ayres." Illustrator unknown. Publication: Nuovo Giornale Illustrato Universale, page 108., Circa 1860-1880 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Turning the First Turf of the Buenos Ayres Great Southern Railway." Illustrator unknown. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 477., 1864 May 14 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Ruins of the Retiro Barracks, At Buenos Ayres, After the Late Explosion." Illustrator unknown. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 80., 1865 January 28 (Box 1)
  - Title: "Views of Buenos Aires, with the Exhibition Building." Illustrator unknown. Publication: The Illustrated London News, page 261., 1882 March 18 (Box 1)
  - Title: "The New City of La Plata, Buenos Ayres, The Capital of the Argentine Republic." Publication: The Illustrated London Times, page 73., 1884 April 24 (Box 1)
  - Description: Several illustrations of street scenes and buildings in Buenos Aires, as well as portraits of several Argentinian politicians, including the country's president, vice president, and other leaders. Publication: Le Monde Illustré, pages 84-85., 1890 (Box 1)
- Additional material, 1975-1995; Accession 2015-M-051
  This accession consists of late twentieth-century imprints on various trade unions in Argentina. The bulk of the materials comes from the period between 1980 and 1995. It includes materials on Asociación de Trabajadores del Estado (ATE), Federación Argentina de Trabajadores de Luz y Fuerza (FATLYF), Federación Obreros y Empleados Telefónicos de la República Argentina (FOETRA), Sindicato de Mecánicos y Afines del Transporte Automotor de la República Argentina (SMATA), Union of State Oil Workers (SUPE), and teachers' unions. Materials consist of directories, contracts, labor agreements, salary agreements, retirement issues, press releases, and other official union documents.
  - Asociación Trabajadores del Estado, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Directories I, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Directories II, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Federación Argentina de Trabajadores de Luz y Fuerza
    - General I, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General II, 1975-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Memorias I, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Memorias II, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Memorias III, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Memorias IV, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Federación de Obreros y Empleados Telefónicos
    - General, 1975-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Memorias, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Memoria Balance, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Press releases, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Salary agreements I, 1975-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Salary agreements II, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Teachers' Unions, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sindicato del Personal de Industrias Químicas y Petroquímicas, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sindicato de Mecánicos y Afines del Transporte Automotor
    - General, 1975-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Memorias I, 1985-1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Memorias II, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Federación Sindicatos Unidos Petroleros del Estado.
    - General, 1975-1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Convenios Colectivos I, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Convenios Colectivos II, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Convenios Colectivos III, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Convenios Colectivos IV, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Women, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Additional material, Accession 2015-M-054
  Materials in this accession include Argentinian election and political ephemera including stickers, broadsides, election lists, publications, posters, candle holders, plastic bags, buttons, newspapers and flyers. Many of the items were distributed for the May 14, 1989 election.
  - Alianza de Centro Ephemera, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Christian Political Parties Ephemera, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Christian Political Parties Broadsides, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Izquierda Unida Ephermera, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lists of Endorsed Candidates, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newspapers, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Partido Justicialista Ephemera, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Partido Socialista Democrático Ephemera, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Partido Socialista Democrático Publications, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Partido Socialista Popular Ephemera, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Peronista Publications, 1954-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Peronista Publications - JOTAPE, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Unión Cívica Radical Ephemera, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Unidad Socialista Broadsides, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unión Socialista Ephemera, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Menem Button, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2 Menem Campaign Candleholders, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Menem Election Flag, 1988-1989 (Folder 6)
  - Posters
    - Election Poster, 1988-1989 (Folder 6)
    - Juventud Democrata Cristiana Poster, 1988-1989 (Folder 6)
    - Partido Justicialista Poster, 1988-1989 (Folder 6)
    - Peronista Poster, 1988-1989 (Folder 6)
    - Unión Cívica Radical Poster, 1988-1989 (Folder 6)
    - Unidad Socialista Posters, 1988-1989 (Folder 6)
    - Menem Posters, 1988-1989 (Box 4)